[Music]
in 2018
one of the best-selling blood pressure
drugs valsartan sold as divan
was found to be contaminated by the
probably carcinogenic nitrosamine known
as
n-nitrosodimethylamine or ndma
it's believed that approximately 20
million people worldwide were prescribed
the drug tainted with this contaminant
whose cancer risk has been shown to
exceed that of
many known potent carcinogens including
asbestos
benzoate pyrene and pcbs
the u.s food and drug administration
estimated that taking the drug for a few
years could cause cancer in as many as 1
in 8 000 people
whereas the european equivalent of the
fda estimated the cancer risk could be
as high as 1 in 5 thousand
it is unlikely researchers wrote in the
spring 2019 paper that drugs like
valsartan are a unique case and indeed
a few months later the fda announced it
found ndma in ranitidine renitidine the
acid reflux drug sold as xantac
is one of the most prescribed drugs on
the planet in addition to being sold
over the counter give people a single
tablet and the amount of ndma flowing
through their bodies jumps up more than
a hundredfold
then in 2020
some formulations of metformin a popular
diabetes drug sold as glucophage were
found to be contaminated the finding of
ndma and common medicines led the fda to
call for the immediate withdrawal of all
zantac from store shelves yanking the
drug from the market because their
testing
showed ndma levels could in some
circumstances exceed the acceptable
daily intake limit of 96 nanograms per
day it was so bad that the fda found
levels of this carcinogenic contaminant
ndma and zantac similar
to the levels you would expect to be
exposed to if you ate grilled or smoked
meats
wait what
ndma has not only been found in
contaminating drugs it is a known
byproduct of pesticide manufacturing
leather tanning and tire plants and is
found in multiple food and beverages
including processed meat and beer
now that we know ndma can transfer
through the placenta this may explain
the relationship between maternal cured
meat consumption during pregnancy and
the risk of childhood brain tumors
for example hot dog consumption during
pregnancy may increase childhood brain
tumor risk by 33
or sausage consumption by 44 percent
baking consumption may increase
childhood brain tumor odds by 60 or 70
percent
but it's not just processed meat
researchers have found it in poultry
products as well
a single serving of chicken
contains more than 100 nanograms of ndma
remember how the fda said the acceptable
daily intake limit is 96 nanograms per
day half of a chicken breast contains
110.
now raw poultry doesn't have any it's
the cooking process in fact the dry heat
cooking of meat like broiling or
grilling even creates airborne ndma
releasing this very potent carcinogenic
compound into the air so even if you're
only getting a salad or something in a
charcoal grill restaurant just being
indoors or meat is being cooked could
pose a significant cancer risk
these nitrosamines are also found in
cigarette smoke and pressure was put on
the tobacco industry to try to remove
them arguing that there's simply no
logical reason why removable carcinogens
should be allowed to remain in a
consumer product that's the same reason
zantac was yanked from store shelves
okay so let me get this straight
one of the best selling drugs in history
was pulled from the market a drug that
brought in billions of dollars
because it contained a probable
carcinogen that exceeded the acceptable
daily limit but there may be more of the
contaminant in a single serving of
chicken
so my question is why aren't they
pulling the poultry off the shelves as
well
[Music]
you